A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Middle East and Africa, Office Files of Lowell Hardin FA1528
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Middle East and Africa, Office Files of Lowell Hardin
1968-1982
Rockefeller Archive Center
Hardin, Lowell S.
Ford Foundation
FA1528
7.02 Cubic Feet 18 boxes (16 letter document containers and 2 legal document containers)
7 Cubic Feet 18 boxes (16 letter document containers and 2 legal document containers)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accessions 2019:046 and 2019:053.
Arrangement
Series 1: International Agriculture Research and Training
Subseries 1: Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) and International Agricultural Research Centers, 1968-1980
Subseries 2: Arid Lands Agricultural Development Program (ALAD), 1971-1975
Subseries 3: Program Strategy Records and Information Papers on Agricultural Programs, 1968-1982
Biographical / Historical
Lowell Stewart Hardin earned a bachelor's degree in agricultural economics from Purdue University in 1939 and his doctorate from Cornell University in 1943. He was a member of the Purdue agricultural economics department faculty from 1943 to 1965 and served as department head from 1953 to 1965.
In 1965, Hardin left Purdue to join the Ford Foundation as a program officer within the Latin American Office setting up agricultural training programs. Hardin and his colleagues at the Ford and Rockefeller Foundations worked to create international agriculture research stations, first in the Philippines, then in Mexico. Ultimately, there were seventeen centers around the world in a global network covering the major food commodities. International staffs under international boards of directors were supported to do research and training, primarily in sustainable methods for plant and animal production to increase the available food supply.
In 1970, Hardin became a program officer with the Office of the Vice President within the Ford Foundation's International Division, Middle East and Africa program. During his 17 years with the Foundation, he was a principal architect of the worldwide system of international agricultural research centers.
Hardin returned to Purdue in 1981, and he became the Assistant Director of International Programs in Agriculture, a position he held until 2007. Hardin died in 2015 at the age of 97.
Scope and Contents
Lowell Hardin worked for the Ford Foundation from 1965-1981 in the field of international agriculture research and training. This collection of Hardin's office files contains reports related to agricultural training and production, budget and program planning documents from agricultural research and training centers, planning documents and reports from the Arid Lands Agricultural Development (ALAD) Program in Beirut, and meeting materials from the Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR).
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Agriculture -- Ford Foundation; Agricultural Economics; Ford Foundation; Green Revolution; International agricultural research; International agricultural research and training centers
- International Agriculture Research and Training, 1968-1982; 1; 7.02 Cubic Feet 16 letter document boxes and 2 legal document boxes
  - Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) and International Agricultural Research Centers, 1968-1980; 1
    Scope and Contents
    CGIAR Technical Advisory Committee (TAC) meeting materials, international agricultural centers' budget and program materials, and reports
    Biographical / Historical
    The Consultative Group for International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) was established on May 19, 1971, to coordinate international agricultural research efforts and achieve food security in developing countries. CGIAR arose in response to the widespread concern in the mid-20th century that rapid increases in human populations would soon lead to widespread famine. Originally, CGIAR supported four international research centers: the International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) (est. 1960), the International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT) (est. 1963), the International Center for Tropical Agriculture (CIAT)(est. 1962), and the International Institute of Tropical Agriculture (IITA) (est. 1967).
    - Mailing to some field, Pereira Team on Irrigation/Water Management, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sudan Survey, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
      Agricultural Economics and Statistics in the Ministry of Agriculture, Food, and Natural Resources, Khartoum, Sudan
      Organization and Administration of Agricultural Research in the Sudan
      Sorghum Research in Sudan
      Potato Research in the Sudan
      Wheat Research and Production in the Sudan
      Crop Production and Agronomy in the Sudan
      Groundnut Production and Research in the Sudan
      Agricultural Extension As It Relates to Agricultural Research
    - Centers - Technical Advisory Committee (TAC) Nomination Responses, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Mailing - Various Field Offices - Daniel Hillel Paper on Water Management, 1978 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) Meetings, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) Meetings, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
    - Technical Advisory Committee Meetings, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 11, Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Technical Advisory Committee Meetings, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Technical Advisory Committee Meetings, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Centers - Program Budget, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) Correspondence and Report Drafts, 1971-1979 (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
      Costs and Benefits of Agricultural Research: State of the Art and Implications for the CGIAR, C. Edward Schuh and Helio Tollini
      Assessing and Monitoring International Agricultural Research, C. Edward Shuh and Helio Tollini
      The Rural Development System of the People's Republic of China: Impressions and Questions, Sterling Wortman
      Constraints Influencing China's Agricultural Performance, Dwight H. Perkins
      Reflections on China
      Discussion Notes, A Perspective on Rural Development and the Green Revolution in Asia, Walter P. Falcon
    - Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) - Technical Advisory Committee Meeting Report Drafts, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Programs and Budgets of the International Agricultural Centers, 1974 June (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - International Agricultural Centers Discussion of 1974 Programs and Budgets, 1973 June (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - International Agricultural Centers Analysis of 1973 Programs and Budgets, 1972 June (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Biographical and Related Materials, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 130)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted - Personnel - Open in 2042
    - Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) Memos, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Technical Advisory Committee Meetings, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Center Trustees (Prospective), 1977-1980 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Centers - Prospects for Dir. Gen., 1976-1980 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) Pamphlets, 1979 October (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Q&A on Agriculture, Science, and the Developing World, A Briefing on International Agriculture Research and Training Centers Supported by the Rockefeller Foundation and the Ford Foundation, 1968 October (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) Report of the Task Force on International Assistance for Strengthening National Agricultural Research, 1978 August (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Bound Memoranda Regarding International Agricultural Centers, 1975 May-June (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Arid Lands Agricultural Development Program (ALAD), 1971-1975; 2
    Arid Land Agricultural Development (ALAD) was a program of the Ford Foundation that operated in Lebanon in the 1960s and 1970s. The program's goals were to make the best use of limited water resources, to improve production of staple food crops in a region of major food gaps, and to address the complex integration of crop and livestock production in the dry areas. ALAD later became the International Center for Agricultural Research in the Dry Areas (ICARDA), established in 1975.
    Primarily reports and program planning materials
    - Progress Report of the Near East Cooperative Sorghum and Millets Crop Improvement Program, Arid Lands Agricultural Development Program, The Ford Foundation, Beirut, Lebanon, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - 1974 Annual Narrative Report for ALAD-DAP 689-0187, 1975 April (Box 5, Folder 31)
      Foundation-Administered Program Grant No. 06890187
    - Agriculture Technology for Developing Countries, Technical Series Bulletin No. 15, The Buffalo Gourd (Cucurbita foetidissima) HBK, A Potential Crop for the Production of Protein, Oil, and Starch on Arid Lands, Agency for International Development, 1975 January (Box 5, Folder 32)
      Includes photograph of unidentified man standing with Cucurbita foetidissima root weighing 145 kg
    - Progress Report of the Near East Cooperative Broadbean, Lentil, and Chickpea Crops Improvement Program, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Present Livestock Situation in the Near East and the Possibility of Developing Integrated Crop-Livestock Farming Systems, 1973 March (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - The Potential for Increasing Cereal and Livestock Production in Algeria: A Report Prepared for CIMMYT, Mexico and the Ministry of Agriculture and Agrarian Reform, Algeria, E.D. Carter, 1974 October (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - The Domestication of a Wild Perennial, Xerophytic Gourd, Cucurbita Foetidissima, The Buffalo Gourd, Lawrence C. Curtis and N. Rebeiz, 1974 January (Box 5, Folder 36)
      Progress Report I - A Search for Superior Plants
      Progress Report II - The Discovery of Antherless and Male Sterile Plants and Their Potential Role in the Production of Hybrid Seed for Commercial Planning
      Progress Report III - A Search for Superior Buffalo Gourd - Continued
      Progress Report IV - A Search for Superior Buffalo Gourd Plants and (1) Their Use in Producing Hybrid Seed for Commercial Planting and (2) Their Use for Forage, Erosion Control and Land Cover
    - Summary Report on the Regional Sheep and Forage Production Workshop, February 11-14, 1974, Lebanon, 1974 October (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Handbook for Food Legume Training Course, Lebanon, 1975 March-October (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Sheep Breeding Project at Terbol Suggestions for the Future, Prepared by Helen Newton Turner and Carroll W. Fox, 1974 March (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Selected Agricultural Statistics in Ranked Order for Countries of the Near East Region (Extended and Revised), 1975 July (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Opportunities for an Accelerated National Potato Improvement Program for Lebanon by John Niederhauser and Richard T. Wurster, International Potato Center, Lima, Peru, Consultants for ALAD Program, Beirut, Lebanon, 1973 March (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Selected Agricultural Statistics in Ranked Order for Countries of the Near East Region, Oddvar Aresvik and Majed Kreidy, Beirut, Lebanon, 1972 September (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Discussion Paper on the Need for a Permanent Agricultural Research and Training Institute in the Near East, Beirut, Lebanon, 1972 March 11 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - The Lebanese Seed Program: Recommendations for Strengthening the Seed Multiplication, Seed Distribution and Seed Quality Control System in Lebanon, by Johnson E. Douglas, Seed Production Specialist, The Rockefeller Foundation (2 copies), 1972 November 30 (Box 6, Folder 56-57)
    - The Arid Lands Agricultural Development Program: Outlook and Planning Review, Beirut, Lebanon (2 copies), 1971 April (Box 6, Folder 58-59)
    - The Arid Lands Agricultural Development Program: Outlook and Planning Review - Observations, Implications and Suggestions, Beirut, Lebanon, 1971 April 20-22 (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Arid Lands Agricultural Development Program Review, 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 61, Box 7, Folder 62)
      Correspondence and memos
      Budget information
      Reports:
      A Preliminary Proposal on a Food Legume Improvement Program for the Middle East, Dr. K. O. Rachie
      The Arid Lands Agricultural Development Program for Accelerating Economical Food Production in the '70s
      Discussion Paper on Program Alternatives for ALAD as Related to Possible Budget Limitations
      Plant Disease Situation of High-Yielding Dwarf Wheats in Asia and Africa, E.E. Saari and Roy D. Wilcoxson
      A Bibliography of Reports Prepared or Distributed by the Ford Foundation's ALAD Staff
      Background Papers: ALAD Discussion
      Lists of People who received literature, correspondence or seeds - Cucurbita foetidissima
      ALAD Regional Staff List with Start/Termination dates
      The Sorghum and Millets and Food Legume Programs Interim Report
      Contribution of Animal Breeding to Improved Sheep Production in the Middle East and North Africa Region, Helen Newton Turner
  - Program Strategy Records and Information Papers on Agricultural Programs, 1968-1982; 3
    - The Ford Foundation, International Division, Summary Tables, FY 1975 and Earlier Years, 1976 April 26 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - The Ford Foundation, International Division, Summary Tables, FY 1974 and Earlier Years, 1975 May 19 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - The Ford Foundation, International Division, Summary Tables, FY 1976 and Earlier Years, 1977 February 23 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - The Ford Foundation, International Division, Summary Tables, FY 1977 and Earlier Years, 1978 March 16 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - The Ford Foundation, International Division, Summary Tables, FY 1980 and Comparisons with Earlier Years, 1981 May 22 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - The Ford Foundation, International Division, Summary Tables, FY 1981 and Comparisons with Earlier Years, 1982 September 30 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Small Farm Production and Capital Accumulation: Potato Producers in Carchi, Ecuador - A. A Case Study Survey, B. Technological Policy Recommendations for Small Scale Potato Growers in Carchi, Ecuador, undated (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - In-House Report 1975 - Farming Systems Program, International Institute of Tropical Agriculture, Ibadan, Nigeria, 1976 February (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - International Centers - Grant Documents, 1968-1978 (Box 7, Folder 71, Box 8, Folder 72)
      Sections include: ALAD/ICARDA, CIAT, IITA, IFPRI, CGIAR
    - February 2 Workshop: Papers Presented, 1979 February 2 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT) and International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) - Grant and Budget Information, 1967-1978 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - International Agricultural Research Centers - Reports, Memos, and Budget Information, 1973-1978 (Box 8, Folder 75-76)
      International Crops Research Institute for the Semi-Arid Tropics (ICRISAT), International Center for Agricultural Research in the Dry Areas (ICARDA), International Food Policy Research Institute (IFPRI), and Consultative Group (CG) - Technical Advisory Committee (TAC) of Consultative Group for International Agricultural Research (CGIAR), Arid Lands Agricultural Development Program (ALAD), International Center for Tropical Agriculture (CIAT), International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT), International Potato Center (ICP), International Rice Research Institute (IRRI), West Africa Rice Development Association (WARDA), International Laboratory for Research on Animal Diseases (ILRAD), International Livestock Center for Africa (ILCA), International Board for Plant Genetic Resources (IBPGR)
    - Harris, John, "Capitalism and Peasant Farming: A Study of Agricultural Change and Agrarian Structure in Northern Tamil Nadu, 1977 September (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - Consultative Group for International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) - Reports, 1973-1979 (Box 9, Folder 78-80)
      The Consultative Group and the International Agricultural Research System: An Integrative Report
      Selected Notes: Meetings of Directors, International Agricultural Research Centers, Feb. 11-16, 1973
      Secretariat Observations 1979/80 Program and Budget
      Costs and Benefits of Agricultural Research: State of the Art and Implications for the CGIAR, C. Edward Shuh and Helio Tollini
      TAC Meeting Reports
      A Classified Bibliography of Investment in Agricultural Research: Extent, Limitations, and Consequences
      TAC Review of Priorities For International Support to Agricultural Research (Progress Report to CGIAR)
    - Consultative Group on Agricultural Research (CGIAR) Meetings, 1971-1975; Meetings, 1976-1978, 1971-1978 (Box 9, Folder 81, Box 10, Folder 82-83)
    - Joint Council Notes Newsletter, Joint Council on Food and Agricultural Sciences; Report Assessing Global Food Production and Needs, 1979-1980 (Box 10, Folder 84)
    - Regional Wheat Workshop: Volume I - Diseases, The Ford Foundation, Beirut, Lebanon, 1972 February 14-17 (Box 10, Folder 85)
    - Regional Wheat Workshop: Volume II - Agronomy, The Ford Foundation, Beirut, Lebanon, 1972 February 14-17 (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - Regional Wheat Workshop: Volume III - Appendices, The Ford Foundation, Beirut, Lebanon, 1972 February 14-17 (Box 11, Folder 87)
    - International Fund for Agricultural Development - Press Materials, 1978-1979 (Box 11, Folder 88)
    - International Fund for Agricultural Development - Annual Report for 1979, 1980 January (Box 11, Folder 89)
    - Middle East and Africa - Agricultural and Resources Staff Seminar, Khartoum, Sudan, Lee Travers, 1980 January 6-9 (Box 11, Folder 90)
    - Agricultural Sector Analysis, undated (Box 11, Folder 91)
    - Middle East and Africa Reports, 1976-1979 (Box 11, Folder 92, Box 12, Folder 93-94)
      Terminal Report to Ford Foundation, Gordon McLean, Ph.D., Agricultural Team Leader - Cairo
      Progress Report of the IRRI/ALAD Rice Improvement Program in Egypt, 1974
      Survey of Agricultural Research in the Sudan, Capabilities, Scope, Potentials, and Priorities, Prepared for the International Workshop on Agricultural Research and Development in the Sudan, 1976
      Sudan Agricultural Research Capabilities, The Joint Team Report to the Minister of Agriculture, Food, and Natural Resources
      Comments on IADS Report
    - Susan Sechler Chrons, 1981 April-July (Box 12, Folder 95)
    - Papers by G. Edward Schuh, 1974-1976 (Box 12, Folder 96-98)
      A Review of the Workshop on Time Allocation in Rural Households, with Special Emphasis on the Role of Women
      Some Thoughts on Agricultural Policy and Decision Making
      Planning for Hunger Prevention
      Imperfections in the Labor Market and Policy for the Rural Poor in Brazil
      The Role of Agricultural, Food, and Research Policy in Meeting Food Needs
      Un Modelo de Politica Para La Industria Brasilena de Ganado Vacuno
      The Influence of the Emerging Countries on the U.S.: Trends, Recent Developments, and Some Policy Choices
      Some Notes on the Political Economy of Rural Development in Latin America
      General Economic Policy as a Constraint to the Development of Agriculture
      Rural Development and Rural Employment: An Overview of the Problems
      The Exchange Rate and U.S. Agriculture: Reply
      The Rationality of Economic Policy
      A Metademand Function
      The Contributions of Agricultural Research to the Achievement of Development Goals
      Impact of the International System on Research Capacity and on Agricultural Productivity: Comments
      Data Needs for Policy Analysis
      The International Dimension to our Food Prices
      Theoretical Considerations for Cost of Production Studies
      Effective Integration of International Agricultural Training into On-Going Campus Programs
      Exchange Rate Policy and Agricultural Development in Brazil
      Labor Absorption: Some Evidence from Brazil on the Importance of Appropriate Factor Price Policy
      The Metaproduction Function, Technology and Trade in Agricultural Products
      The New Macroeconomics of Agriculture
    - Staff Meeting on Agriculture, Natural Resources and Related Rural Development, 1981 January 13-15 (Box 12, Folder 99)
    - Conference on Resource Allocation and Productivity in International Agricultural Research, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 100-101)
    - Middle East and Africa - Agricultural and Resources Seminar, Khartoum, Sudan, 1980 January 6-9 (Box 13, Folder 102)
    - East Africa Trip Reports, Correspondence - Joseph V. Remenyi, 1977-1978 (Box 13, Folder 103)
    - African Development Council, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 104)
    - David C. Korten's Papers/Community Organization, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 105)
    - Outlines, 1981 June 11 (Box 13, Folder 106)
    - The Ford Foundation's Strategy in Agriculture - A Twenty-Five Year Perspective, David E. Bell, Lowell S. Hardin, and Joseph V. Remenyi, undated (Box 14, Folder 107)
    - Correspondence and Notes Related to ALAD: An Evaluation, 1978-1980 (Box 14, Folder 108)
    - Council on Foreign Relations, 1978-1979 (Box 14, Folder 109)
    - Public Policy, Joseph V. Remenyi, 1977-1978 (Box 14, Folder 110)
    - "Feeding the Hungry: A 25 Year Perspective" Brochure Draft, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 111)
    - African Background Information, Joseph V. Remenyi, 1972-1974 (Box 14, Folder 112)
    - Responses on Reed Hertford's Proposal for Country Studies, 1978-1979 (Box 14, Folder 113)
    - International Association of Agricultural Economists, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 114)
    - Files of Norman R. Collins - Memos, Reports, Correspondence, etc., 1981 (Box 15, Folder 115)
    - Korean Agricultural Sector Analysis and Recommended Development Strategies, 1971-1985, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 116)
      Rossmiller, George E. - Field Project Director
      Carroll, Tom W.
      Kim, Sang Gee
      Kim, Young Sik
      Manetsch, Thomas J.
      Suh, Han Hyeck
      Kim, Dong Hi - Director, AERI
      Johnson, Glenn L - Project Director
    - Water Resources of India and their Utilisation in Agriculture, C. Dakshinamurti, A. M. Michael, Shri Mohan, Water Technology Centre, Indian Agricultural Research Institute, New Delhi, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 117)
    - A Generalized Simulation Approach to Agricultural Sector Analysis with Special Reference to Nigeria, Michigan State University, 1971 November 30 (Box 16, Folder 118)
    - Water Management Research in Arid and Sub-Humid Lands of Less Developed Countries - Annual Report - Colorado State University, 1975 December (Box 16, Folder 119-120)
    - Consortium for International Development, Factors Affecting Losses from Indus Basin Irrigation Channels, Thomas J. Trout, Water Management Research Project, Colorado State University, Water Management Technical Report No. 50, 1979 July (Box 16, Folder 121)
      Colorado State University
      University of Arizona
      University of California at Davis and at Riverside
      Utah State University
      New Mexico State University
      Oregon State University
      Texas Tech University
      University of Idaho
      Washington State University